# 哈喽大家好
Hi everyone!
# 我兄弟从江西过来带了3只竹鼠
My bros have come to me from Jiangxi with 3 bamboo rats.
# 在这里
They're here.
# 然后他们一到了就帮我翻地
Upon arrival, they helped me plow my field.
# 这一块地已经翻好了
They've already finished the field over here.
# 我本来打算是种花的
My planning was to plant some flowers.
# 然后正好他们来的话
And now, as they're already here,
# 没有什么好招待他们的就将就这只竹鼠烤一只
and I don't have anything decent to serve them. So I am going go grill one of the bamboo rats.
# 我们大家吃饱了才有力气干其它的活儿 对吧
So that we can have a big feast to fuel up ourselves for the farm work, right?
# 反正来没什么好招待你的只能将就你的竹鼠
I have nothing decent for you. Perhaps we can only bet your bamboo rat's understanding.
# 嘿嘿
He he
# 噢哟
Oyo!
# 沺沺让一下
Stay away, Tian Tian!
# 小心哦
Watch out!
# 拎它尾巴就可以了
You can simply hold its tail.
# 太凶了这个
It's too fierce!
# 这个是母的吗
This is a female?
# 嗯
Yup!
# 这个还是交给你来吧
I think I've better leave it to you.
# 好吧
Alright!
# 哎呀
Bamboo rat, bamboo rat!
# 竹鼠竹鼠
Aya
# 它咬破了一点点
It has chewed up a bit.
# 哇
Wa!
# 那行 那你来烧我去准备烧烤架
Okay! You'll take care of the rat and I'll get the barbecue stand ready.
# 可以可以没问题
Sure, sure! No problem!
# 哇变成金黄色的了
Wa! It becomes golden yellow.
# 把它清洗一下
I'll have it washed.
# 这个肉这么厚
Look! It's so thick here.
# 不凶的话我都把它留下来了
I wouldn't have taken it with me if it were not that fierce.
# 好 现在我们把它腌一下
Alright! Let's marinate it for a while.
# 弄点姜跟葱
Put some ginger. This is scallion.
# （缺失）
Put some oyster sauce.
# 下次你也可以像这样放点蚝油
Next time you, you can also put some oyster sauce.
# （缺失）
It matches well with bamboo rats.
# 你们家有没有料酒
You have cooking wine here?
# 料酒 料酒用完啦
Cooking wine? I have used up the cooking wine.
# 都用完了
Oh really?
# 对呀
Yup!
# 茅台的就没有
And I don't have Maotai.
# 稍微整咸点哦 头回（上次）没得咸味得
Mak'it a bit more salty. It ain't nut salty las' time.
# 要得
Allite!
# 这不就是料酒吗
Isn't it cooking wine too?
# 茅台料酒没有
Yours is Maotai.
# 你们那个没有
I don't have it here.
# 给它按按摩
Give it a massage.
# 按摩一下
Right, a massage.
# 好肥呀这个竹鼠
This bamboo rat is very fat.
# 烤的话一定要肥一点
A fat one is needed for grilling.
# 它瘦的话就没什么味道了
Otherwise it doesn't taste anything.
# 然后我们就上烤架
Then, you can put it onto the stand.
# 来先腌制吧 放旁边去腌制
No hurry. Put it there to keep it marinated.
# 我们去生火
Let's set the fire.
# 来吧
Come on!
# （缺失）
Here is your final destination.
# 这条上烤架
the barbecue stand.
# 这个烤起安逸
Grillin' dis is gut!
# 直接就上架啰
So I'll put it onto the stand.
# 上架了
Go ahead.
# 我估计最少要烤一个小时
I think it takes at least an hour.
# 烤一个小时那我们轮流烤吧
It takes an hour. Let's take turn.
# 可以呀
Alright!
# 这个肉吃起很闷 很闷人啊
Da meat, da meat's greasy, greasy.
# 不得闷 这个烤
No greasy.
# 还不闷 头次我吃过啊 闷得很
Ver' greasy! Las' time we ate, ver' greasy!
# 闷得很
Ver' greasy?
# 谁让你养那么肥呀 兄弟
How can you let it be that fat man?
# 它吃太多了 不是我养那么肥 其它都是很苗条的 就它吃的最多
It's because it ate too much. I didn't do anything. Others are still very slim.
# （缺失）
It ate the most.
# 看来长肥也是一个
It seems that getting to fat is also a...
# 不能太肥
Yeah, they shouldn't get too fat.
# 我们休息一会儿吧 轮流来
Why don't we take a break? Let's take turn.
# 你先来 好不
Can you be the first one?
# 我先来 我先来就我先来
Sure! I will be the first one.
# 我们休息一会
Let's take a break.
# 好香的
It smells good.
# 熟都还没有熟就开始有香味了
It's still raw, but it already smells so good.
# 把这个油刷起来
Brush the oil onto it.
# 然后把这个芝麻撒均匀一点 看着很好看 很美观
And then sprinkle the sesame evenly.
# （缺失）
Then it looks good, gorgeous.
I'll when it's cooked.
# 这等烤熟了之后我们再来 现在搞上去会把芝麻烧焦的
The sesame will get scorched if I put it too early.
# 这个烤很好烤
It's nice to have this stand.
# 上次就用那个竹签
Last time we used the bamboo sticks.
# 竹签没那么方便
The bamboo sticks are a bit more tricky.
# 这个压着它动不了
It won't be moving when it's pressed.
# 上次我看见你哪里那个白的竹鼠很漂亮很美观
The white bamboo rat that I've seen last time is really pretty, very gorgeous.
# 是啊 看看就可以了 那个不好吃的
He looks good only. The taste is awful.
# 那个很好看
It looks really good.
# 很好看 不好吃
Good look, awful taste.
# 那白的是我们震仓之宝
The white rat is our hidden gem.
# 要是我们这里养那个竹鼠
Raising bamboo rats here,
# 竹子没有问题
we have infinite supply of bamboos.
# 遍山都是
Bamboos are everywhere.
# 到时候可以在这边做几个池子 放几个竹鼠
Perhaps you can build some cells and keep some bamboo rats.
# 我带十几个竹鼠过来
I can come again with a dozen of them.
# 想吃的时候就可以烤一下
So that you can have one to grill whenever you want.
# 开始冒油啦
The oil is coming out.
# 我们这个竹鼠要是做成辣竹鼠肯定很受欢迎
I'm thinking of making a preserved bamboo rats. I am sure that it will be very popular.
# 是哦
Indeed.
# 是可以考虑一下做成辣竹鼠
We can really consider making one, preserved bamboo rat.
# 我看一下烤成什么样子了
Let me see. How does it look now?
# 哇 金黄色
Wa! Golden yellow!
# 都烤出油来了
The oil starts coming out.
# 我觉得这个就不用刷油了
I think we don't need to brush any more oil.
# 它自身就有油了
There's already oil from its fat.
# 四斤
4 "jin" (1 "jin" = 500 g)
# 我吃两斤
I'll have 2 "jin".
# 你能吃的下两斤
You think you can finish 2 "jin"?
# 你是人才
Genius!
# 华农哥 这个竹鼠好漂亮哟
Mr Haunong! The bamboo rats is very pretty.
# 你更漂亮哦
You are prettier.
# 是吗 你也很漂亮哦
Really? You are also pretty!
# 我不漂亮
No, I'm not!
# 你比竹鼠都漂亮
You're prettier than bamboo rats.
# 怎么拿我跟竹鼠比
How can I be compared with bamboo rats?
# 我们也有很多粉丝说我们兄弟长得跟竹鼠一样
A lot of fans of mine say that our bro look exactly the same as a bamboo rat.
# 这个我一直以来我不敢说 你知道吗
I've never had the courage to tell you, you know?
# 没事
Never mind!
# 今天终于有人提出来了
Somebody said that finally.
# 这个真的要边烤边吃啊
It needs to be eaten while grilling.
# 这个好像一冷了哪个皮就不脆了
It seems that the skin will be softened once it is cooled down.
# （缺失）
You can eat it.
Are you sure?
# （缺失）
If you are sure, I want this piece (of meat).
# 没好
It's not ready!
# 没熟 哪个不要
No, it's not.
# 哇 好香呀
Wa! It smells so nice!
# 真的很好吃 可以看得到哪个颜色
It tastes really good. You can know from the colour.
# 晶莹剔透
Crystal clear
# 这个好香啊
It smells good!
# 这慢慢越来越香了 特别是快熟的那个时候
The aroma is getting stronger, especially when it's almost done.
# 再考二十分钟差不多了
20 more minutes, and it's almost done.
# 很香
It smells good!
# 好 现在该划一下了
Alright! Now I gonna cut it a few times.
# 先割块肉给我吃下
Get a piece of meat for me!
# （缺失）
Wut?
# 我尝一下熟了没有
I wanna see if it's done.
# 熟了没有
Is it alright?
# 这一点点熟了 里面不知道熟没有
Here is alright, not sure inside.
# 里面也快了
Soon I think.
# 我要吃
Give me a piece!
# 你也要啊
You want it?
# 我要吃肩膀
I want its shoulder.
# 好 肩膀
Alright! Shoulder.
# 烫不烫哦
Is it hot?
# 有一点点烫
A bit.
# 好烫
Very hot!
# 啊
Ah!
# 烫不烫
Is it hot?
# 不烫 很香的
No! It's tasty!
# 好了 不烫了
It's alright now.
# 真好吃
It's so tasty!
# （缺失）
Very salty!
# 哇 这个
Wa! This is...
# 哦 这个皮呀
Oh! The skin!
# 这个声音 你看脆了
Can you hear the sound? It's crispy now.
# 很香哦
It smells good!
# 好香啊
Really good!
# 酱油
Soy sauce
# 要燃哦
It burns.
# （缺失）
No it doesn't.
# 哇 好香啊
Wa! It smells marvelous!
# 太香了
It's just magnificent!
# （缺失）
Iron hand.
Iron hand should have no problems.
# 你不是吧
Yours is not.
# 烫不烫 烫不烫
Does it hurt?
# 不烫
Is it hot?
# 真的好吃 不骗你
It tastes really good! No kidding.
# 爸爸
Daddy!
# （缺失）
Yes?
# 还有几分钟
How many minutes left?
# 很快啦
Soon
# 很香很香我觉得 而且你吃那边的更香
It's really really good! And the side that you've taken, is even better.
# 太香了
Fantastic!
# 可以哦
Not bad
# 你要吃前腿吗
Do you want a forearm?
# 我要吃前腿
I want a forearm.
# 该怎么样子说 烫不烫
Is there something you want to say? Is it hot?
# 谢谢
Thanks.
# 谢谢谁啊
Thank whom?
# 叔叔
Uncle
# 谢谢叔叔
Thank you uncle.
# 那么乖
What a good girl!
# 爸爸给你拿着啊
Daddy will hold it for you
# （缺失）
your forearm.
# 我要撒点料
Let me put on some seasoning.
# （缺失）
I want to eat!
# 这个撒料的话要先搞点油
I need to put on some oil before putting on the seasoning.
# 才粘的住
So that it can be adhered.
# 对 你不搞油粘不住
Yea. It's not possible without the oil.
# （缺失）
I wanna have a bite too.
# 放辣一点好不好
Shall we make it a bit more spicy?
# 没问题
No problem!
# 真的没问题还是假的没问题
Are you sure?
# 这个辣椒很辣的哦
This chili is really spicy.
# 少放点少放点太辣了少放点
Not too much, not too...not too much. Let's have less chili, your chili in Sichuan
# 到了四川来我跟你说这个辣椒
So you are now in Sichuan, you know, our chili is
# 好 可以了可以了可以了
Enough enough enough enough
# 好啦好啦好啦 太辣了
It's far too spicy!
# 没事 烤的时候它会掉下去的
No it isn't. The chili will slip away.
# 孜然粉
Cumin powder
# 孜然跟辣椒放起好美观哦看到
Cumin powder looks gorgeous together with chili.
# 安逸 肯定啰
Nice!
# （缺失）
Certainly!
# 好了好了不要了 放那么多
Enough enough enough. No more. Not too much.
# 花椒就少放一点 好不好
Let's have less Sichuan chili, shall we?
# （缺失）
Sure, less
# 这里总共就只有这么一点
We don't have much here anyway, just a bit.
# 这下就看到更安逸了
With the sesame, it tastes even better.
# （缺失）
It looks even better.
# 哇 看到好好看哦
Wa! It looks very pleasant.
# 我好想吃啊
I really wanna taste it.
# 可以了哟
It's alright now!
# 开工开工开工
Let's go, let's go, let's go!
# 这样子
How about...
# 嗯 聪明
Um, clever
# 哇 这样也想得到
Wa, genius!
# 聪明聪明
Smart, smart
# 开玩笑
You must be kidding.
# 来
Come on!
# 我们端过去吧
Let's take it over there.
# 端过去吃了
Let's get started!
# （缺失）
Look!
Our, bamboo rat!
# 我们还是不要说太多了 直接吃吧 我好饿
Shall we just get started? Say no more. Let's start. I'm starving.
# 好香
Wonderful!
# 有十个人
There're ten of us!
# 有十个人 怎么数的
Ten? How did you count the number?
# 二四六七
Two four six seven
# （缺失）
What a thigh!
# 八九十
eight nine ten
# 谢谢谢谢谢谢华农哥
Thank you, thank you! Thanks be to Mr. Huanong.
# 农村大腿还是吃小腿呀
Do you want thigh or calf?
# 大腿
Thigh!
# （缺失）
Tail.
# 伯爷 吃这个 你吃得肥的多嘛
Uncle, do you want a more oily part?
# 来吃个肥的 来 伯娘吃这个 吃个腿腿
Come on! This part is fat.
# （缺失）
Come on! Auntie, take it. Have a leg.
# 谢谢谢谢谢谢
Thanks, thanks
# 小哥 来来来
Man! Come here!
# 其实这个辣椒不辣 真的不辣
In fact the chili is not spicy, not spicy at all.
# 不辣呀这个辣椒
Indeed, it's true.
# 再不来我们一会儿就吃完了
We'll finish it very soon if you're not coming.
# 来 吃块皮 很脆的
Get a skin. It's really crispy.
# 哇 这个肥肉你看 这个肥肉特别好吃
Wa! Have a look at the fat!
# 你这个辣椒放那么多都不辣 吓我一大跳 搞的我都
The fat is really tasty.
# 我跟你说不辣吧
The chili is not spicy even you've put so much.
# （缺失）
You scared me.
I've told you already.
# 不敢吃那么多辣椒
I dare not eat too much chili.
# 下次买点辣的
I'll get the spicy one next time.
# 漆二娃 多吃点肥肉噻
Qi Erwa, have more of the oily part.
# 在吃啊
I'm already eating.
# 她净吃瘦肉
She eats only lean meat.
# 净啃瘦的
Only lean meat.
# 今天我兄弟带的这个竹鼠真的很好吃
This bamboo rat from my bro is really delicious.
# 唯一有个缺点就是
The only minus is, you know,
# 这个
you know,
# 胖了一点
A bit too fat.
# 对 胖了一点 那个油我告诉你有这么厚的油
Yea! A bit too fat. The fat is really that thick, you know.
# 毫不夸张
No exaggeration.
# 这个油怎么说呢
The fat is, I mean,
# 如果是干体力活动的人吃起来就很爽
those who do a lot of physical work will certainly enjoy it.
# 像豆腐一样
It's just like tofu.
# 那我们今天就先到这里吧
So that's all for today.
# 拜拜
Bye!